Guide to the Lantern Slide Collection c. 1860-1942 PR 70
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: General Lantern Slides, 1
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Central Park (Box 65, 66, Item PR-070-0001-0253)
    Ice Skating in Central Park (some of these have been moved to the Richard H. Lawrence file); The Terrace; Men involved in ball game in Central Park; drawing of Central Park Drive with cars and pedestrians; Donkeys in Central Park tied up with young boys s
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Chatham Square, 1812 (Box 66, Item PR-070-0001-0254)
    Identical drawings from Valentine's Manual of Chatham Square surrounded by carriages, horses, pedestrians and houses; Chatham Square drawing showing Jewish Burial Ground, Rutgers House, various roads and a bridge.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--City Hall Park, 1819, 1849, 1825, 1827, 1942 (Box 66, Item PR-070-0001-0255)
    City Hall Park with view of American Museum; Views of fountain, pedestrians, fences, surrounding buildings and streets, including Broadway; Views of City Hall with park.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Cold Springs, 1938 (Box 66, Item PR-070-0001-0256)
    Scenic views include: tulip tree, shell heap and Indian cave; View of oldest dwelling in Manhattan.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Collect Pond, 1752, 1797 (Box 66, Item PR-070-0001-0257)
    View of sleigh, horses, bonfire, ice skating and snow at Collect Pond; View of pond surrounded by houses and streets.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--East River Park, 1903 (Box 66, Item PR-070-0001-0258)
    Trees Damaged by storm with benches and view of Brooklyn across East River; Women with baby carriages in East River Park
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Elgin Botanical Garden (Box 66, Item PR-070-0001-0259)
    Duplicates of exterior of garden surrounded by exotic plants and pedestrians--for Valentine's Manual; Duplicates of front of garden with gardening tools and foliage.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Gramercy Square Park, 1905, 1940 (Box 66, Item PR-070-0001-0260)
    Aerial view of Park; view of fountain with benches and foliage; views of park through fence with pedestrians on sidewalk.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Madison Square Park, 1876, 1900 (Box 66, Item PR-070-0001-0261)
    Views of men sitting on park benches and reading newspapers; Aerial views of Madison Square Park; views with churches in background; Madison Square Garden with Liberty Torch; Panoramas of area with park showing carriages and trolley cars; Statues of Chest
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Morningside Park, 1904 (Box 67, Item PR-070-0001-0262)
    Construction of Cathedral of St. John the Divine surrounded by other buildings in background with snow filled park and children in foreground; Carriage on cobblestone streets looking down side of park; Tower at 123rd St. and other military sights.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Park (Box 67, Item PR-070-0001-0263)
    Park on between Washington and West St. on Canal showing footpaths and people sitting on park benches with view of ships in the distance.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Playground (Box 67, Item PR-070-0001-0264)
    Field with swings and tented area surrounded by buildings; located at Ave A and 66th St.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Polo Grounds, 1886 (Box 67, Item PR-070-0001-0265)
    Polo Grounds baseball game (Boston vs. New York) view from stands near catcher's mound showing players and advertisements, including one for Tony Pastor's Theatre; Polo Grounds viewed from Viaduct.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Printing House Square, 1868 (Box 67, Item PR-070-0001-0266)
    Views of Printing House Square with parade passing through and crowds of people, carriages and trolleys; views of surrounding buildings.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Union Square Park, 1859, 1861, 1866, 1860, 1849, 1846, 1904, 1905 (Box 67, Item PR-070-0001-0267)
    Several aerial views of union square, showing surrounding buildings and pedestrians, as well as trees and fountain; images of buildings with and surrounding Union Square showing carriages, pedestrians and trolleys; Views of meetings in Union Square with c
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Parks and Squares--Washington Square Park, 1905 (Box 67, Item PR-070-0001-0268)
    Views of various corners of Washington Square Park, showing pedestrians and benches, as well as fences, grass and surrounding buildings and streets; Site of graveyard; Laying cornerstone for Washington Arch; Temporary Arch; Garibaldi Statue; Holly Statue
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Apartments, 1904, 1924, 1901 (Box 67, Item PR-070-0001-0269)
    Stuyvesant Apartments on East 18th St. view of entrance and view from Irving Place; Gilsey House on Broadway and 29th St. with carriage in foreground, advertisements and pedestrians in back; London Terrace on West 23rd Street in Chelsea with fire hydrant
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Farms, 1750, 1817 (Box 68, Item PR-070-0001-0270)
    Maps of farms of Union Square, Anetje Jans Farm, Trinity Farm and Glass House Farm; Somerindyke Farm on Broadway viewed from a distance; Watt's House in Harlem viewed with fields; McVikar Farm from Delancy estate showing boy with dog, small wooden house a
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes (Box 68, Item PR-070-0001-0271)
    Façade of house covered in ivy; Ferry Point house with view of driveway; rear view of house with ladder leading down to lakefront and surrounded by trees; Views of several houses with porches showing sidewalk and pedestrians, as well as trees; Men standin
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--A through K, 1855, 1725, 1830, 1835, 1905, 1845, 1822, 1856, 1815, 1911 (Box 68, 69, Item PR-070-0001-0272)
    4 similar images and one photograph of Apthorpe Mansion showing grounds, trees and foliage; Home of Dr. Richard Bacon on 104th Street with pedestrians and cars; Bambu House on Madison Square; Johanes Beekman house (Vanderheyden Palace) of Bracebridge Hal
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Astor House (Box 69, Item PR-070-0001-0273)
    Three similar drawings of Astor House on 88th Street near East River showing grounds and trees; Astor Residence on 5th Ave. showing women with baby carriages crossing street, as well as car and other pedestrians, corner view of building and surrounding ar
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Bayard House (Box 69, Item PR-070-0001-0274)
    Bayard House (where Hamilton died) on Jane Street; views of façade.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Beekman House, 1760, 1776, 1850 (Box 69, Item PR-070-0001-0275)
    Four similar views of Beekman house façade and grounds; Headquarters of Gen. Howe; Nathan Hale was confined here before his execution; Aerial view of house and surrounding area, as well as East River; Views of grounds and trees; Interior of "Green Room" w
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Collonade Row, 1833 (Box 70, Item PR-070-0001-0276)
    Collonade Row / La Grange Terrace, one photo with Ivy growing on columns, the other with car in foreground.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Delafield House (Box 70, Item PR-070-0001-0277)
    Baker-Delafield House on 77th Street; duplicate façade views
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Dyckman House (Box 70, Item PR-070-0001-0278)
    Dyckman House in Washington Heights with views of exterior with porch and staircase, as well as kitchen
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Fonthill, 1848 (Box 70, Item PR-070-0001-0279)
    Forrest Residence ("Fonthill") Castle and Garden views on 22nd Street near Hudson River.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Franklin Mansion (Box 70, Item PR-070-0001-0280)
    Franklin Mansion--similar views of façade with carriages and carts in front.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Goelet Mansion, 1905 (Box 70, Item PR-070-0001-0281)
    Union Square area Goelet Mansion on 19th Street and Broadway--view of building with pedestrians and cobblestone streets.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Gracie Mansion (Box 70, Item PR-070-0001-0282)
    Gracie Mansion with view of East River Park sidewalks and benches, as well as house and grounds
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Hamilton Grange, 1802, 1900 (Box 70, Item PR-070-0001-0283)
    Hamilton Grange on Convent Ave.--views of house and grounds with large trees, fences and stairs; proposal for Grange design.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--L through Q, 1854, 1825, 1904, 1800, 1905, 1858, 1837, 1816 (Box 70, 71, Item PR-070-0001-0284)
    Lane Cottage near Hell Gate showing road and cows; Latimer House on 3rd Ave. and 88th Street showing front steps and trees; Lawrence House on West End Ave. and 75th St. with view of foliage; Leggett House (first house lighted by gas) with pedestrians; Lin
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Morris-Jumel Mansion (Box 71, Item PR-070-0001-0285)
    View of house with peacock statue and man; Mansion with American Flag; Frontal and side views of mansion with trees; View of front porch.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Morris-Jumel Mansion, interiors (Box 71, Item PR-070-0001-0286)
    Hall of Jumel Mansion with maid, showing view of paintings and fireplace in adjoining room; Washington Room with bedpost, fireplace and mantle mirror, as well as other furniture, vases and candlesticks.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--R through V, 1866, 1861, 1892 (Box 71, 72, Item PR-070-0001-0287)
    Richmond Kill Mansion view with two men fishing; Riker House on East River at 75th St. from Valentine's Manual--view includes house and woman walking past well; Mansion of Beverly Robinson near Hudson River--view of house and driveway, as well as grounds
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Schermerhorn House (Box 72, Item PR-070-0001-0288)
    Views of front and back of Schermerhorn House near York Ave., including grounds, foliage and river.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Smith's Folly, 1806 (Box 72, Item PR-070-0001-0289)
    Architectural views from road and river; Reconstruction views with grounds and driveways showing pedestrians; 61st near East River façade views.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Stuyvesant House, 1953 (Box 72, Item PR-070-0001-0290)
    Main Entrance with gates; Façade view with trees--79th Street at 5th Ave.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Stuyvesant House, interiors, 1953 (Box 72, Item PR-070-0001-0291)
    Second floor dining room showing ceramics on exhibition prior to auction; Second floor dining room alcove showing glassware; Ground floor kitchen; Ground floor Reception room and Library; Second Floor Drawing Room; Third floor library; Entrance Hall; Four
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--Ver Planck House, interiors (Box 73, Item PR-070-0001-0292)
    Ver Planck House on Wall Street-- View of drawing room with dishes, fireplace, clothes, furniture and paintings; View of dining table with chairs, painting and dishes.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Residences--Houses and Homes--W through Z, 1857 (Box 73, Item PR-070-0001-0293)
    Waddell Mansion on Fifth Ave. and 37th St. viewed with carriages, horseback riders and pedestrians on streets; Walton House on Pearl St. showing façade and pedestrians; Ward House on 59th St. and 10th Ave. view of front yard showing fence and street; Warr
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Schools and Colleges (Box 73, Item PR-070-0001-0294)
    Illustrations of public school-related concepts, such as "Fighting for a Chance to Learn" or "Importance of Instruction and Punishment" and classroom tools; advertisements for school openings; Teacher's notes (including J.J. Astor, Dewitt Clinton and John
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Schools and Colleges, by name, 1881, 1904, 1805 (Box 73, Item PR-070-0001-0295)
    Buckwheat Field with Barnard College in background and view of sidewalk; Views of City College of New York, including surrounding buildings and streets; Cooper Union on Astor Place with view of surrounding streets, including fourth Ave., pedestrians, and
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Schools and Colleges, by number, 1897 (Box 74, Item PR-070-0001-0296)
    P.S. 1 on Henry Street with view of façade, street and carriage; P.S. 3 with American flag and carriage full of barrels passing by, as well as small boy standing in front of building; P.S. 15 on Ave. B and 15th Street--view of boys' Clay modeling classroo
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Schools and Colleges, interiors (Box 74, Item PR-070-0001-0297)
    Boys' and Girls' assembly images of children in lecture hall; Sewing and Carpentry classroom shots from unknown school; empty classroom view at unidentified school; drawing of Allen St. School classroom with teacher and students; auditorium of Board of Ed
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Schools and Colleges--Columbia University, 1758, 1760, 1790, 1816, 1830, 1872 (Box 74, Item PR-070-0001-0298)
    "Kings College" on Park Place viewed from a distance with surrounding buildings; Façade view of college with front lawn; hand-colored view of college with surrounding buildings, streets and landscape, including street lighting; University viewed from a di
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Schools and Colleges--General Theological Seminary (Box 74, Item PR-070-0001-0299)
    Bell from Seminary photographed as museum object; View of Seminary building covered in ivy, showing surrounding trees and street lighting; Door of old seminary with stairs leading to it, fence, and ivy-covered brick; Drawing of Seminary with passing pedes
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Schools and Colleges--New York University, interiors (Box 74, Item PR-070-0001-0300)
    Drawing of Professor Morse's room at NYU from which the first message was sent--showing podium and student seats.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Schools and Colleges--New York University, 1903, 1850 (Box 74, Item PR-070-0001-0301)
    Main Building with view of trees and Washington Square Park; University Building with view of snow and Washington Square Park, as well as passing pedestrians; Washington Square Park and New York University buildings on surrounding streets--aerial view wit
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets, 1820, 1825, 1830, 1831, 1861, 1893, 1896, 1904, 1905, 1914, 1942 (Box 75, 76, 77, Item PR-070-0001-0302)
    Amity Lane near West 3rd St. and Washington Square--alley full of wooden boxes and view of doorway to street on opposite side; S.E. Corner of Bank and Bleecker Streets with views of shoeshine stand, stable and pedestrians, as well as stores and lamp posts
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets, avenues by number, 1861, 1905 (Box 76, Item PR-070-0001-0303)
    West side of 2nd Ave. b/t 115th and 116th Sts.. With toy store and apartments; 4th Ave. b/t 10th and 11th Sts.. With carriages and assorted buildings, as well as pedestrians; S.E. corner of 4th Ave at 18th St. with view of Claredon Hotel, pedestrians and
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets, streets by number, 1817, 1904, 1905, 1909, 1857, 1869, 1861, 1888 (Box 76, Item PR-070-0001-0304)
    View of 4th St. b/t/ McDougal and 6th Ave. from New York Tribune--drawing of houses and trees; 4th St. with view of Dry Dock Savings Bank and surrounding area, including tracks from street-railroads; J. Schneider Furs and vine-covered Apartment Houses on
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets, unidentified (Box 76, Item PR-070-0001-0305)
    Unidentified streets, including view of a Bus stop, road paving, commercial buildings, churches, trolleys, banks and pedestrians.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Battery Place, 1831, 1904 (Box 76, Item PR-070-0001-0306)
    Steamboat Wharf at Battery Place with pedestrians, steamboats, sailboats and industrial buildings; Castle Garden and view of ocean at Battery Place with view of park; Battery Place West of Washington Street with Pennsylvania Rail Road Pier, carts, pedestr
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Bowery, 1838, 1904 (Box 77, Item PR-070-0001-0307)
    N.E. Corner of Bowery and Division St. showing pedestrians, pig, and commercial building; Bowery South at Canal Street with trolley tracks, carriages, pedestrians and elevated railroads; Bowery view with elevated trains, vendors, sailors, beggars and oth
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broad Street, 1642, 1659, 1942 (Box 77, Item PR-070-0001-0308)
    Broad Street looking North towards Wall Street with view of buildings and crowd gathered in middle of street; North on Broad Street from Exchange Place cars lining sidewalks and commercial and government buildings; Canal in Broad Street with sailboats and
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Below Battery Place, 1904, 1910, 1850 (Box 77, Item PR-070-0001-0309)
    Looking up Bway from State St.; Broadway facing south at Bowling Green with view of Bowling Green Offices building, carriages and pedestrians; View of No. 1 Bway
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Battery Place to Exchange Place, 1848 (Box 77, Item PR-070-0001-0310)
    Various panoramas of city blocks on East and West sides of Broadway from #1 through #57. View of Broadway north of Bowling Green; Panorama of Bway with signs for coal yard and warehouses; Bway north from Aldrich Buildings; View north from 1 Broadway (nea
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Exchange Place to Wall Street, 1942, 1904 (Box 77, Item PR-070-0001-0311)
    Broadway looking north from Exchange Alley with views of pedestrians, street lamps, cars, and Trinity Church tower; Broadway looking south at Rector Street with pedestrians, trolley, policeman and Shearson, Hamill and Company building; Broadway looking no
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Wall Street to Fulton Street, 1904, 1898 (Box 77, Item PR-070-0001-0312)
    Broadway south from Cedar Street with Trinity Church, pedestrians and carriages; Broadway and Trinity Building with graveyard view; Panoramas of Cortlandt to Bowling Green and Dey St.; East Side of Broadway north from Maiden Lane with telephone wires, ped
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Fulton Street to Chambers Street, 1850, 1904, 1942, 1905, 1830 (Box 77, Item PR-070-0001-0313)
    Broadway and Ann Street with view of Astor House, American flags and pedestrians, as well as numerous carriages; Panorama view of Broadway at Fulton Street (Tullis View); Broadway and Murray Street with drugstore, pig and water pump; Bway at Barclay Stre
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Chambers Street to Canal Street, 1904, 1857, 1885 (Box 78, Item PR-070-0001-0314)
    Bway South between Pearl St. and Duane St. with sporting goods store, Abercrombie and Fitch building, pedestrians and carts; Bway and Chambers Street with pedestrians, trolleys and building construction; East on Orankliu? St. with street lighting, carriag
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Canal Street to Houston Street, 1800, 1840, 1904 (Box 78, Item PR-070-0001-0315)
    Bway between Canal St. and Astor Pl. showing Stone Bridge with pedestrians and houses; Bway panorama between Howard and Grand with carriages and buildings; Bway north at Pine Street with the Burul? Bldg., cobblestone streets, pedestrians and church.
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Houston Street to Fourteenth Street, 1904, 1860 (Box 78, Item PR-070-0001-0316)
    Bway north at Houston Street with awnings, pedestrians, stores and trolley speeding past; Tearing up Bway at 9th Street for Cable Road near Clinton Pl. with view of Grace Church from South, showing pedestrians and construction workers, as well as retail s
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Fourteenth Street to Twenty-third Street, 1860, 1828, 1908, 1818 (Box 78, Item PR-070-0001-0317)
    Looking up Bway towards Union Square with pedestrians, carriages and buildings; Junction of Bway and Bowery Road (Union Square) with houses and stagecoach; Broadway with Manhattan Bank of the City of New York on East Side, trees and grass, as well as hous
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Broadway--Above Twenty-third Street, 1905, 1902, 1904, 1864 (Box 78, Item PR-070-0001-0318)
    Broadway at 42nd Street on East Side with women crossing street near Rectors and other stores; Old homestead at Bway and 50-51st Streets showing bar/café and theatre advertisements; Striker's Lane at Broadway and 53rd St. showing snow, houses and street l
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Canal Street, 1904, 1897, 1940, 1942 (Box 78, Item PR-070-0001-0319)
    Canal Street at Broadway looking southwest with National City Bank of New York building, as well as pedestrians and cars; Canal Street east of Elm Street with wagons and carts, lamp posts, and large billboards in background; Corner of Canal and Division S
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Fifth Avenue, 1885, 1920, 1879, 1842/50,1881,1919, 1892 (Box 78, 79, Item PR-070-0001-0320)
    5th Ave. south at 21st St. with view of what may be the Church of the Ascension, as well as a carriage, trees, pedestrians and surrounding buildings; Fifth Ave. looking toward 63rd St.with St. Luke's Hospital and surrounding area; Flatiron building and ae
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Five Points, 1827, 1904 (Box 79, Item PR-070-0001-0321)
    Boys standing in doorway near carts on cobblestone street with laundry lines behind them; Five Point Clothing House with pedestrians and people gathered out front at intersection of Worth St.--view of trolley lines and surrounding buildings; Commercial bu
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Mott Street, 1904 (Box 79, Item PR-070-0001-0322)
    Images of Mott Street looking north (?) at buildings decorated with various flags and Chinese lanterns; Mott street buildings with awnings and apartments with carriages and carts outside, as well as men on sidewalks; drawing of Mott Street-Chinatown area
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Park Avenue, 1897, 1889 (Box 79, Item PR-070-0001-0323)
    Various views of Park Ave. pavements--before and after laying by Barber Asphalt Paving Co. showing cobblestone streets with buildings/apartments in distance; Asphalt on foundation of old stone block with view of men standing near steamroller (with operato
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Park Row, 1904, 1942 (Box 79, Item PR-070-0001-0324)
    Park Row looking south from City Hall Park with stores, cars, pedestrians and snow, as well as view of St. Peter's Church; Park Row at Nassau Street looking south with view of stores and statue of Benjamin Franklin; Park Row with carriages, trolley track
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Riverside Drive (Box 79, Item PR-070-0001-0325)
    Riverside Dr. at 97th Street looking North; Viaduct from Claremont in distance on Riverside Drive in Harlem; Benches facing Hudson River on Riverside Drive; apartment buildings and trees on Riverside Dr.`
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--Wall Street, 1831, 1942, 1948, 1850, 1835, 1834, 1842, 1831, 1820 (Box 79, Item PR-070-0001-0326)
    Barber Photo of Wall Street prior to repaving with view of cobblestones and buildings; Wall St. viewed from Trinity Church with horse-driven sleighs, various buildings and pedestrians; View of Wall St. with Merchant's Exchange, Drexel Building, and surrou
  - New York-NYC-Manhattan--Streets--William Street, 1800 (Box 79, Item PR-070-0001-0327)
    Four identical view of old buildings on William St. looking from corner of Liberty St. towards Maiden Ln., showing pedestrians and houses; made for Valentine's Manual.